Guide to the William A. Speck Collection of Goetheana: Manuscripts
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Box and Folder List, 1542-1967; 7.51; (18 boxes)
  - FUNKE, ERICH
    - Goethe-Jahr (1949) in U.S.A., n.d. (Box 5, Folder 195)
      10 l.; 28 cm., 2 copies.
      Published in German quarterly v. 24,
      1951.
  - GALLOWAY, JANET A.
    - ALS: Queen Margaret College, Glasgow, to Alfred Richards, Princeton University, 1907 Oct 12 (Box 5, Folder 196)
      6 p.; 12 x 20 cm.
      With two impressed seals of Glasgow
      University.
  - GEIGER, LUDWIG, 1848-1919
    - 6 LS: Berlin, to William Alfred Speck, 1898-1903 (Box 5, Folder 197)
      13 p.; 23 x 14 cm.
      Letters dated: May 19, Jun. 17, Oct.
      6, 1898; May 27, Jun. 25, 1900; and
      May 7, 1903.
      3 Postcards: Berlin, signed, to
      William Alfred Speck. Dated Aug. 13,
      1899, Apr. 4, 1900 and Jun. 17, 1903.
      All bearing on pictorial contributions
      from the Speck collections for the
      Goethe-Jahrbuch, edited by Geiger.
  - GEIST, JOHANN JAKOB LUDWIG, 1776-1854
    - ALS: Weimar, to Christian Heinrich Ramann, 1803 Nov 23 (Box 5, Folder 198)
      1 p.; 14 x 19 cm.
      Geist, secretary and valet to Goethe.
  - GELLERT, CHRISTIAN FÜRCHTEGOTT, 1715-1769
    - ALS, to Graf Hans Moritz von Brühl, 1755 Mar 8 (Box 5, Folder 199)
      2 p.; 19 x 22 cm.
    - ALS, to Graf Hans Moritz von Brühl?, 1755 Apr 3 (Box 5, Folder 200)
      4 p.; 19 x 22 cm.
      Enclosure: German copy and English
      translation of this letter.
      Chiefly Gellert's reaction to Samuel
      Richardson's The History of Sir
      Charles Grandison.
    - ALS: Leipzig, to "Theuerste Frau Gräfin" Gräfin Brühl?, 1764 Jul 4 (Box 5, Folder 201)
      2 p.; 18 x 22 cm.
  - GERSDORFF, ERNST CHRISTIAN AUGUST VON, 1781-1852
    - ALS: Weimar, to "Hochwohlgebohren Freiherr", 1840 Aug 8 (Box 5, Folder 202)
      3 p.; 22 x 26 cm.
      Gersdorf, prime minister of the Grand
      Duchy of Saxe-Weimar-Eisenach,
      represented Grandduke Karl August at
      the Congress of Vienna. He sends on
      request a short sketch of his life
      corrected and enlarged from
      Graebner's book on Weimar. Whether
      this material is meant for a new
      edition of Graebner, or another
      venture is difficult to determine.
      The autobiographical sketch not
  - GERSTENBERGK, GEORG FRIEDRICH KONRAD LUDWIG VON
    Dates: 1780-1838
    - ALS: Weimar, to Herrn Prof. F. Schütz, 1829 Jan 14 (Box 6, Folder 203)
      3 p.; 21 x 25 cm.
  - GLEICHEN-RUSSWURM, EMILIE HENRIETTE VON, 1804-1872
    Full name: Emilie Henriette Friederike
    (von Schiller), Freifrau von Gleichen-
    Russwurm
    - ALS: Würzburg, to Frau Doktorin Knude in Kissingen bei Adam Heilmann, [1859?] Jun 10 (Box 6, Folder 204)
      3 p.; 14 x 21 cm.
      Signed: Emilie Gleichen-Schiller.
      Seal removed.
    - ALS: Greifswald ob Bonnland, to Frau Doktorin Knude, 1859 Nov 2 (Box 6, Folder 205)
      4 p.; 14 x 22 cm.
      Signed: Emilie von Gleichen-Schiller.
      The letter accompanied a lock of
      Schiller's hair.
  - GLEIM, JOHANN WILHELM LUDEWIG, 1719-1803
    - ALS: Halberstadt, to Adam Oeser, 1777 Jun 12 (Box 6, Folder 206)
      4 p.; 18 x 25 cm.
      Enclosure of "ein Blättchen" on the
      subject of the recent drowning of
      an unnamed youth, not present.
  - GOEBEL, JULIUS, 1857-1931
    Papers on Goethe. n.d.
    - In case; 32 cm. Some papers in manuscript form only, some in both manuscript and printed form. Included are three manuscripts by Rudolf Hildebrand. Typewritten list inserted at front. The case is lettered on back: The Julius Goebel memorial collection: Goethe.
    - See: Bound Volumes, folder 805
  - GÖCHHAUSEN, LUISE ERNESTINE CHRISTIANE JULIANE VON
    Dates: 1752-1807
    - ALS: Weimar, to unidentified recipient, 1776 Aug 29 (Box 6, Folder 207)
      2 p.; 12 x 19 cm.
  - GÖSCHEN, GEORG JOACHIM, 1752-1828
    - ALS: Grimma, to Johann Ambrosius Barth, 1826 Jan 20 (Box 6, Folder 208)
  - GOETHE, AUGUST VON, 1789-1830
    - LS: Weimar, to "Ew Wohlgeb.", 1826 Oct 4 (Box 6, Folder 209)
      1 p.; 24 x 20 cm.
      Informing the recipient that he will
      be in Jena on the next day or the
      following one for the reopening of
      the Jena Academic Library.
    - ALS: Weimar, to Wilhelm Ternite, 1829 Nov 4 (Box 6, Folder 210)
      Signed: J. A. von Goethe.
    - ALS: Weimar, to Christian Ernst Friedrich Weller, 1826 Aug 17 (Box 6, Folder 211)
    - Document, signed: Weimar, to Herzogl. Rent Amt zu Heussdorf, 1816 Jul 31 (Box 6, Folder 212)
      1 p.; 20 x 30 cm.
      Signed: J. A. Goethe; co-signers are
      Voigt, Gersdorf, Büttner, Ridel,
      Rühlmann, Stichling [and one
      undeciphered].
      A report on the tax charged for
      messenger service.
  - GOETHE, CATHARINA ELISABETH (TEXTOR), 1731-1808
    - Sample of her handwriting: An Herrn Unzelmann (Box 6, Folder 213)
      1 p.; 10 x 17 cm.
      Personal red seal attached. Mounted.
  - GOETHE, JOHANN CASPAR, 1710-1782
    - AL (copy), jointly with his wife: Frankfurt am Main, to G. F. E. Schönborn, 1776 Jul 24 (Box 6, Folder 214)
      4 p.; 21 x 25 cm.
      In the handwriting of Alfred
      Nicolovius.
      Advising of Goethe's visit to Weimar
      during the winter 1775/76, and of
      his recent appointment as
      Legationsrat by Duke Carl August.
      The original letter was presented to
      the Weimar Landesbibliothek in 1825.
      [Zu Goethe's Jubelfeier zu Weimar. Am
      7. November 1825]
      With: Other material related to
      Goethe's Jubelfeier in 1825.
  - GOETHE, JOHANN WOLFGANG VON, 1749-1832
    - Longer Works
      - Apophthegmen von G. aus den Jahren 1807-14, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 215)
        AMs (copy), 4 p.; 20 x 34 cm.
        In Friedrich Wilhelm Riemer's hand.
        Pencil note at top of p. 1: Aus d.
        Tageb[üchern] copiert von R.
        26 items, 1 with pencil correction.
      - My life's early years. Dichtung und Wahrheit. n.d. (Box 6, Folder 216-220a)
        828 l.; 28 cm.
        Typescript (chiefly original, a few
        leaves are carbon).
        English translation of Dichtung und
        Wahrheit by Williamson, Green, and
        Schreiber.
        With ms. corrections in pencil or ink
        in 3 different handwritings, incl.
        that of C. F. Schreiber.
        With: Typescripts of variants of 6
        poems, 6 l.; 28 cm., with ms.
        corrections.
        With: Biographical fragments,
        typescript (carbon), 30 l; 28 cm.,
        contents: Tales of my mother; An
        early period; A later period; Jacobi
        The beginning of my friendship with
        Schiller; Herder; Anna Amalia; He
        restoreth my soul.
      - Des Epimenides Erwachen, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 221)
        AMs, 3 p.; 21 x 34 cm.
        Fragment of Epimenides.
        In Friedrich Wilhelm Riemer's hand,
        with stage directions pencilled in.
        This version differs variously from
        the first printing in 1815.
      - Faust d'après Goethe en VI actes. La tragédie 1re partie, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 222)
        136 p.; 21 x 17 cm.
        Ms. copy in an unidentified hand, in
        German.
        Transcription in German script of the
        scenes up to and incl. "Der
        Nachbarin Haus."
        The passage of line 562 to 601
        transposed after line 851; lines 967-
        969 are variant; lines 970-1021,
        1346, 1970-1982, 2195-2218, 2659-
        2666, 2695-2704, 2721-2724, 2831-
        2840, part of 2849-2878, 2985-3002
        are omitted. - Cf. Goethes Werke,
        Jubiläums-Ausgabe.
        Bound in green linen with title:
        Purchased from Colbeck Radford & Co.,
        Ltd., London, October 5, 1933.
      - Faust 2.Th. Vor dem Palaste. Lines 8628-8637, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 223)
        AMs, 1 p.; 13 x 21 cm.
        Ms. note on verso: Handschrift meines
        Schwiegervaters. Ottilie von Goethe
        with 4 red seals showing the Goethe
        coat-of-arms.
        Ms. note on slip pasted on verso: ...
        obtained from Madame de Goethe ... in
        1839. J. C. Reynolds of Richmond Va.
        Another ms. note: This stanza of Faust
        from the original was given to me by
        Gov. J. C. Reynolds Jan. 14, 1879.
        Mary Phelps Montgomery.
      - Offene Gegend (Box 7, Folder 224)
        AMs, 2 p.; 20 x 34 cm.
        Fragment of the 5th act of Faust,
        comprising almost half of the episode
        entitled Offene Gegend. Differs
        slightly from the version printed in
        the Weimar Ausgabe.
        Gift from Ottilie von Goethe to Mrs.
        Anna Jameson, with the latter's
        endorsement dated Nov. 25, 1833.
        With: Reproduction "no. 5 of Facsimiles
        and reproductions of unique or rare
        items from the William A. Speck
        Collection of Goetheana in the Yale
        University Library," 1926.
      - Faust; a tragedy, by J. Wolfgang von Goethe. n.d.
        - AMs, 3 v. (5-112 p.; [112] p.; [85] p.); 23 cm. First part of Goethe's "Faust" translated into English verse by Jonathan Birch. Some pages are blank. With copious corrections by the author, many in pencil; a few text variants on slips inserted. At end of each, vol. notes, various drafts of poems, etc. Interleaved with a copy of Faust, eine Tragödie, von Goethe. Neue Aufl. Stuttgart und Tübingen: J. G. Cotta, 1831. The translation of Pt. I was first pub. London: Black and Armstrong; Leipzig: F. A. Brockhaus, 1839.
        - See: Bound Volumes, folder 806a-c
      - Faust; a tragedy in two parts by J. Wolfgang von Goethe. n.d.
        - AMs, 80, 8 p., 78 l.; 31 cm. Second part of Goethe's "Faust" translated into English verse by Jonathan Birch. Incomplete draft. In portfolio. First 80 p. bound in in paper covers, 8 p. and 78 l. bound separately, its covers lost. Some of the 78 l. have text in pencil or ink on verso, chiefly variants. Translation of pt. II, act I, scene Lustgarten, line 6003 to act 4, scene Auf dem Vorgebirg, line 10454; with ms. correction in ink or pencil. On inside front cover, p. 79-80 first count, and inside back cover are notes in pencil or ink, and English and German versions of a poem, beginning: Come dearest, come [Komm, Liebchen, komm]. On leaf attached at front a short note on the translation, dated October 1843. The translation of pt. II was first pub. London: F.A. Brockhaus, 1843. In portfolio with this are 14 mounted clippings from English newspapers containing reviews of Birch's and other translations of Goethe's Faust, and some items of general contents; the clippings had been mounted on pages of the ms. over the text.
        - See: Bound Volumes, folder 807
      - But shall a poodle also mumble?, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 225)
        AMs, 7 p.; 17 x 21 cm. and 5 p.
        11 x 17 cm.
        English translation from Goethe's
        Faust, scene Studierzimmer, lines
        1209-1322.
        Translated by George Henry Borrow.
      - Walpurgis Night, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 226)
        AMs, 23 p.; 21 x 17 cm.
        With typed transcription.
        Faust, lines 3835-4222.
        With Borrow's ms. corrections, some
        in pencil.
      - Another earlier draft of lines 4144- 4175, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 227)
        2 p.; 17 x 11 cm.
        Printed in v. 8 of the "Norwich
        edition" of Borrow's works.
        For further description and
        information of these three mss. see
        Lillian Espy (Reed) Atkins,
        Fragmentary English translations of
        Goethe's Faust; Ph.D. Thesis, Yale
        University, 1937, p. 162-206; also
        William A. Speck, George Borrow and
        Goethe's Faust, Publications of
        Modern Language Association, v. 41,
        p. 167-178.
        With: Another earlier draft of lines
        3871-4061. Translated by George
        Henry Borrow. 11 p.; 11 x 18 cm.
      - From the translation of Goethe's Faust, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 228)
        2 l.; 27 x 20 cm.
        Autograph ms., signed.
        Translated by Frank Claudy.
        Translation of Pt. I, pact scene,
        lines 1714-1759.
        Published in Faust; a tragedy by
        Johann Wolfgang von Goethe; the
        first part, 1886.
      - Selections from Goethe's "Faust", translated by Albert G. Latham, Monkseaton, Northumberland, 1932 Jun 1 (Box 7, Folder 229)
        AMs, 1 p.l., 14 p.; 34 cm.
        "These transcriptions from my
        translations of the "Faust" [pt. 1
        and 2] published in Messrs. J.M. Dent
        & Sons' "Temple Classics" (Part I,
        1902; Part II, 1905) and afterwards
        in "Everyman's Library", 1908, were
        made at the request of my friend and
        sometime student, Professor Andrew
        Keogh, of the Yale University
        Library", signed, Albert G. Latham.
        Accompanied by a typed letter, signed,
        to Mr. Keogh, dated June 23, 1932.
      - Faust. Parts I and II (Box 7, Folder 230)
        93 l.; 29 cm.
        English translation by George Madison
        Priest of Johann Wolfgang von
        Adapted for the Goethe bicentennial
        festival production of the City
        College of New York Dramatic
        Society; directed by Samuel L.
        Sumberg, at the Pauline Edwards
        Theatre, May 27, 28, 1949.
        Program laid in.
        With ms. notes.
      - Faust, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 231)
        123 p., 15 p. of sketches; 28 cm.
        Carbon typescript.
        English translation of Faust, Part 1,
        by Graham Stanhope Rawson.
        Script for the Theater Guild production
        in 1928, with their light, property,
        and scene plots, and stage
        directions.
        Rawson's stage version was published in
        London in 1936.
        Copy given to Alice Raphael by Lawrence
        Langner, with her notes on the front
        cover.
        With two clipped reviews of the Theater
        Guild production laid in, one by
        Albert Carroll and one by John Whyte,
        together with an ALS from Whyte to
        Alice Raphael, 1928 Nov. 22.
        Additional information on this
        production will be found in the YCAL
        Theater Guild file.
      - Faust, a tragedy. By J. W. V. Goethe. Translated in the original metres. 1. and 2. parts. 1869 May 15
        - AMs, 432, i.e. 427, p.; various sizes of pages, some oversized ones folded, bound to 27 x 23 cm. Translated by Bayard Taylor (1825-78). Taylor's working copy with copious corrections and variant passages, some in pencil. Gift of Mrs. Edward S. Harkness. First published in 1870.
        - See: Bound Volumes, folder 808
      - Selection from Taylor's translation of Goethe's Faust, part II, Vor dem Palaste, lines 9594-9836, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 232)
        AMs, 9 l.; 25 x 20 cm.
        The passage is from Act III: "Chorus.
        Speakest thou as if within were
        spaces roomy as the world is"
        through "Euphorion. Dream then who
        may ...," p. 285-299 of the printed
        edition, Boston, 1871.
        With: A covering letter from Bayard
        Taylor to Mrs. Anne Lunch Botta,
        Apr. 4, 1872, presenting this ms.
        to her.
      - Selection from Taylor's translation of Goethe's Faust, part II, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 233)
        AMs, 1 p.; 18 cm.
        The passage is from Act III,
        Euphorion: "I will not longer ..."
        through "Thine, hers and Mine?"
        It differs widely from the version in
        the printed edition, Boston, 1871,
        p. 293.
      - Goethe's Faust. A beginning; in United States vernacular "fluid fidelity", n.d. (Box 7, Folder 234)
        Typescript (original), 46 l.; 28 cm.
        With a second copy of part of p. 31
        and one page of errata.
        Ms. note at front of typescript:
        Translated by Mr. H. Turm,
        discoverer and owner of the
        disputed Goethe portrait by Dawe.
        Translation by Turm of Faust I
        through line 1408.
        With dedication to Carl F.
        Schreiber, and an introductory
        poem.
      - French translation of several verses from Goethe's Faust, pt. I, "Zwinger" scene, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 235)
        AMs, 1 p.; 20 x 27 cm., mounted.
        In upper right hand corner: 109.
        Translated by Alphonse Marie Louis de
        Lamartine.
        "This is the autograph of Lamartine,
        the poet. F.L." in upper left corner.
        A rough draft, prose description
        alternating with attempts at
        versification.
      - Faust von Goethe, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 236)
        AMs, 1 p. l., 20 p.; 17 x 20 cm.
        Yiddish adaptation by A. Tannenbaum,
        translated to page 14 by Leopold
        Adler.
        A critical sketch of Goethe's drama
        and Gounod's opera, in Leopold
        Adler's handwriting.
        Translated from the Yiddish version -
        cf. book in the Speck Collection
        (Sa4 910).
        Enclosure: ALS from Leopold Adler to
        Georg Ehrhardt, May 18, 1911,
        Teplitz-Schönau, and autograph note
        Über Jargon, in Ehrhardt's hand.
      - Der Raub der Helena. Scenen aus dem zweiten Theile des "Faust" von Göthe in 2 Aufzügen. n.d.
        - AMs, 155 p.; 22 x 18 cm. Transcriber unknown. Adapted for the royal court theater by Gutzkow, with music by Reissiger. Multi-colored board cover. "Text-Manuscript ... mit dem Theaterzettel der ersten Aufführung im Kgl. Hoftheater in Dresden, zu Goethes hundertjähriger Geburtsfeier am 28. August 1849 ... Nicht im Druck erschienen!" - Ehrhardt's catalogue note no. 1114.
        - See: Bound Volumes, folder 809
      - Stage adaptation of Faust Part I, by Johann Wolfgang Goethe, 1949 Mar (Box 7, Folder 237)
        1 p.l., 138 l.; 28 cm.
        Typescript (carbon)
        In black snap binder.
        Translated by Alice Raphael.
        "Acting version prepared by Frank
        McMullan and Alois Nagler, for
        production by the Yale University
        Department of Drama," March, 1949.
        With: Xerox copies of press clippings,
        one including a picture of Mrs.
        Raphael, tipped in on inside front
        and back covers.
      - Goethe - Urfaust. Translation compiled by Thomas G. Neumiller for production at the Yale School of Drama, Oct. 20-24, 1964, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 238)
        64 l.; 30 cm.
        Title mounted on blue binder.
        Processed from typescript.
        With translator's corrections.
        Chiefly in verse.
        Presented by T. G. Neumiller in partial
        fulfillment of the requirements for
        the degree of Master of Fine Arts.
        For further notes on the translation,
        sources used, etc., see his MFA
        thesis production book (Yale Drama
        School Library, call no. Be40.G549).
        Accompanied by TLS to Kurt von Faber
        du Faur, May 29, 1965.
        With: Theater program of the
        performance of Goethe's Urfaust at
        the Yale School of Drama, October
        20-24, 1964.
      - Faust. Dramatisches Gedicht von Goethe, in 6 Aufzügen. n.d.
        - AMs, 1 p. l., 60, 68, 150, 95, 73, 39 p.; 21 x 18 cm. Transcriber unknown. Adapted for performance by Karl Seÿdelmann. Blue paper cover. This version was first played at Stuttgart, March 2, 1832 - Gräf, Goethe über seine Dichtungen, Drama II, p. 9. "Hermann Veyin?" written on t.p. in different handwriting.
        - See: Bound Volumes, folder 810
      - Proömium zu Hermann u. Dorothea, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 239)
        2 p.; 11 x 19 cm.
        Autograph ms. (copy)
        A poem written in December 1796 as a
        sequel to the Xenien-Kampf.
        Begins: Also das wäre Verbrechen?
        First pub. as introduction to his
        Hermann und Dorothea, Vieweg
        edition, 1820.
      - Hermann und Dorothea, Paris, 1860 (Box 8, Folder 240)
        1 l., 157 numb. p.
        English translation of Goethe's
        Hermann und Dorothea.
        Handwritten ms. with corrections.
        The translator is unidentified.
        In verse, but not in the original
        meter.
      - Iphigenia in Tauris, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 241-241a)
        3 p. l., 101 numb. l.; 29 cm.
        2 copies.
        Typescript (xerox copy).
        Iphigenie auf Tauris by Evelyn
        Solann; as presented at the
        auditorium of the New York library of
        the Performing Arts at Lincoln
        Center, Jun. 10, Jun. 12 and Jun. 13,
        1967 [c1957].
        Both copies autographed by all the
        actors, including the translator, who
        took the role of Iphigenie.
      - The Sorrows of Werter; a German story. 1785?
        - 273, 3 p., 1 l., incl. music; 20 cm. Manuscript copy in an unidentified calligraphic hand. Copied apparently from the new edition by Dodsley, 1784 (In Speck Coll.: z Jc2 779 784) Title of pt. 2 (p.143-273) in red and black. "The Sorrows of Charlotte at the Tomb of Werter," composed by J. Moulds, March 1785. With music: p.238-240. "The Force of Love being a Sequel to the Sorrows of Werter, Composed by John Moulds ... March 1785" [with music]: p.271-273. Bookplate of Robert Watts; crest of Sir Thomas Phillips, of Middle Hill, stencilled on fly-leaf.
        - See: Bound Volumes, folder 811
      - Topkbato-Tacco. 1868
        - 284 p.; 26 x 21 cm. Taskin's Russian translation in blank verse of Goethe's Torquato Tasso. Transliterated title: Torkvato Tasso. Calligraphic hand, evidently of a professional copyist; the signature to the dedication, however, appears to be in the translator's own hand. With dedication to "Your Imperial Highness," presumably Grand Duke Alexander, subsequently Emperor Alexander III. Translator states in the dedication that he is a native of Siberia.
        - See: Bound Volumes, folder 812
      - Elective Affinities, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 242-243c)
        47 galley proofs for p.3-155; 160 l.
        numbered 157-316, typescript for
        p.155-305 of the edition published
        at Chicago by Henry Regnery, 1963.
        English translation by Mayer & Bogan
        of Johann Wolfgang von Goethe's
        Wahlverwandtschaften.
        With profuse pencil corrections in
        both galleys and typescript; 1 l.
        ms. corrections, 1, 2, 2 typed l.
        attached to l.17, 23, 25, and 30,
        respectively.
        The edition was pub. with an
        introduction by Victor Lange.
      - Hints, (their value), n.d. (Box 8, Folder 244)
        AMs, 2 p.; 19 x 12 cm.
        Fragment from Thomas Carlyle's English
        translation of Goethe's Wilhelm
        Meister (3rd book, 8th chapter),
        1824, v. 1, p. 288.
        Copy in John Howard Payne's
        handwriting.
    - Lyric Poetry
      - Als an der Elb' ich die Waffen ihm segnete, Jena, 1820 Sep 27 (Box 8, Folder 245)
        Autograph poem, signed: Goethe
        First printed in Ost und West, Prag,
        1837; later in Weimar Ausgabe with
        title: An Friedrich Förster; also
        in Förster's posthumous papers,
        with title: Drei Begegnungen.
        With an explanatory autograph note
        by Förster.
      - An Carlyle und seine Gattin auf eine zierliche Visitenkarte, Weimar, 1827 Jul 20 (Box 8, Folder 246)
        1 p.; 20 x 20 cm.
        Autograph poem (Draft).
        The title on the ms. reads: An Madame
        Carlyle, nach Edenburg.
        First line: Augenblicklich
        aufzuwarten.
        With: Another poem (Draft) "Mit einer
        Drahtkette" on the same leaf. First
        line: Wirst du in den Spiegel
        blicken.
        With: Another poem (Draft) "Zum
        Regenbogen" on the same leaf.
        Fourth verse only, first line: Aus
        des Regens düstrer Trübe.
      - Dauer im Wechsel - Goethe, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 247)
        AMs, in the handwriting of the
        Marchesa Sarah Margaret d'Ossoli,
        the translator of Goethe's Dauer im
        Wechsel, a poem in 6 stanzas.